A Finding Aid to the George Leslie Stout papers, 1855, 1897-1978, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
George Leslie Stout papers
1855
1897-1978
Archives of American Art
Stout, George L. (George Leslie)
AAA.stougeor
Archival Resource Key
6.4 Linear feet
The papers of conservator and museum director George Leslie Stout measure 6.4 linear feet and date from 1855, 1897-1978. Stout was head of the conservation department at Harvard University's Fogg Art Museum, director of the Worcester Art Museum and Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum in Massachusetts, and a member of the Monuments, Fine Art and Archives (MFAA) Section of the U.S. Army during World War II. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence with family, friends, colleagues and professional associations. There are letters from fellow Monuments Men who served in the MFAA section such as Thomas Carr Howe, Ardelia Hall, Lamont Moore, Theodore Sizer, Langdon Warner and several other prominent arts administrators. The papers also contain biographical materials, writings, sketches and one sketchbook, military records, printed materials, and photographs. There is a 0.2 linear foot addition to this collection acquired in 2020 that includes four diaries, 1944-1946, kept by George Stout as a member of the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section (MFAA) of the U.S. Army (known as the Monuments Men). The diaries describe Stout's experiences surveying war-caused damages in France, Germany, and Japan, and the recovery of Nazi impounded art works. Also included is a hand-made booklet that includes a "Glossary of Cha-no-yu Terms," which consists of quotes about Japanese art and tea drinking.
Biographical / Historical
George Leslie Stout (1897-1978) was a museum director and prominent art conservator in Massachusetts. Stout was head of the conservation department at Harvard University's Fogg Art Museum, and director of the Worcester Art Museum and Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, Massachusetts. During World War II, Stout served in the U.S. Army Monuments, Fine Art and Archives (MFAA) and played a leading role in the protection, location, and recovery of art work stolen by the Nazis.
Born in Winterset, Iowa in 1897, George Leslie Stout was the oldest of six children and attended Winterset High School and served in the U.S. army during World War I. Following the war, Stout studied at the State University of Iowa, received his B.A. in 1921, worked for a few years, and married Margaret Hayes in 1924 with whom he had two sons, Robert and Thomas. He attended Harvard graduate school in 1926 and graduated with a Master of Art in 1929. Stout began working as a lecturer and conservator at Harvard's Fogg Art Museum, later becoming the head of the conservation department in 1933, a position he held until 1947.
During World War II, Stout re-enlisted in the U.S. Navy, having served in the reserves since World War I. Stout was one of the first members of the Monuments, Fine Arts & Archives (MFAA) Section of the U.S. army. He was appointed to the MFAA Section for the Twelfth Army Group in 1944 and was one of the first Monuments Men to arrive at Normandy, France. He was later appointed Lieutenant Commander of the MFAA Section. Many of the Monuments Men's stolen art recovery achievements were directed by George Leslie Stout. Stout supervised the inventory and removal of looted art hidden by the Nazis in the salt mines of Merkers and Ransbach in Thuringia, Germany. Stout oversaw the organization, packing, and shipping of several thousand objects including paintings by Rubens and Goya, along with precious antiquities. At the Altaussee salt mines in Austria, he was in charge of the unit that recovered a large cache of stolen artwork that included Michelangelo's Madonna and Child and the Ghent Altarpiece or The Adoration of the Mystic Lamb by Hubert and Jan van Eyck. There, he also worked very closely with fellow Monuments Men Thomas Carr Howe. Stout went on to locate and recover looted artwork in other repositories in Germany, France, and the Netherlands. He maintained a relationship with many of his fellow Monuments Men after the war.
Stout left Europe in the latter half of 1945, then went to Japan where he served as the Chief of the Arts and Monuments Division at Headquarters of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Tokyo until the middle of 1946. After the war Stout received the Bronze Star and the Army Commendation Medal for his army service and work as a Monuments Man in Europe.
Stout resumed his position as the head of the conservation department at the Fogg Art Museum when he returned to America. In 1947 he became the director of the Worcester Art Museum in Massachusetts where he stayed until 1955, when he became the director of the Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum in Boston where he worked until his retirement in 1970. Stout wrote numerous articles about art conservation and wrote two books: Painting Materials, A Short Encyclopaedia (1942), co-authored with Harvard colleage R. J. Gettens, and Care of Pictures (1948). Stout died in Menlo Park, California in 1978 and was widely recognized as a distinguished art conservator.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as 9 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, circa 1919-1977 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1922-1978 (2.5 linear feet; Box 1-3, OV 8)
Series 3: Writings, 1927-1978 (0.5 linear feet; Box 3-4)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1918, 1943-1978 (1 linear feet; Box 4, OV 8-9)
Series 5: Monuments, Fine Arts & Archives Section Files, 1918, 1942-1955, 1972-1975 (0.5 linear feet; Box 5, 10)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, 1938-1978 (0.1 linear feet; Box 5)
Series 7: Printed Materials, 1926-1977 (0.8 linear feet; Box 5-6, OV 9)
Series 8: Sketchbooks, circa 1924-circa 1938, 1970-1977 (0.1 linear feet; Box 6)
Series 9: Photographic Materials, circa 1855, 1897-1978 (0.2 linear feet; Box 6-7)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection and material lent for microfilming are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 1378, 1420-1425, and 1427 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the microfilmed order does not reflect the current arrangement of the papers.
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2022 and is available on the Archives of American Art website.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
George Leslie Stout donated his papers to the Archives of American Art in 1978. In that same year, Robert Stout, son of George Leslie Stout, loaned four diaries to the Archives of American Art for microfilming. The four diaries were acquired at auction by the Archives in 2020 with generous donations from Paul Neely, David Copperfield in memory of Kelly Asbury, Deborah Lehr and John Rogers, Ambassador Nicholas F. Taubman, The Whitney and Elizabeth MacMillan Foundation, Jeffrey P. Cunard and Mariko Ikehara; The Elbrun and Peter Kimmelman Family Foundation, Inc.; Peter and Paula Lunder; William and Christine Ragland in memory of William McKenzie Ragland Lt. JG, U.S. Navy, Pacific Theater, WWII; The Kurin Family in honor of WWII Veteran Saul Kurin, Paul and Corine Wegener, and Judy and Bob Huret.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with George Stout conducted by Paul Karlstrom in 1978.
Scope and Contents
The papers of conservator and museum director George Leslie Stout measure 6.4 linear feet and date from 1855, 1897-1978. Stout was head of the conservation department at Harvard University's Fogg Art Museum, director of the Worcester Art Museum and Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum in Massachusetts, and a member of the Monuments, Fine Art and Archives (MFAA) Section of the U.S. Army during World War II. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence with family, friends, colleagues and professional associations. There are letters from fellow Monuments Men who served in the MFAA section such as Thomas Carr Howe, Ardelia Hall, Lamont Moore, Theodore Sizer, Langdon Warner and several other prominent arts administrators. The papers also contain biographical materials, writings, sketches and one sketchbook, military records, printed materials, and photographs.
There is a 0.2 linear foot addition to this collection acquired in 2020 that includes four diaries, 1944-1946, kept by George Stout as a member of the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section (MFAA) of the U.S. Army (known as the Monuments Men). The diaries describe Stout's experiences surveying war-caused damages in France, Germany, and Japan, and the recovery of Nazi impounded art works. Also included is a hand-made booklet that includes a "Glossary of Cha-no-yu Terms," which consists of quotes about Japanese art and tea drinking.
Biographical materials include college and graduate school transcripts, various certificates, four small appointment books and passports.
Correspondence is between George Leslie Stout and family, friends, colleagues, professional associations and fellow Monuments Men. Family correspondence is with Stout's immediate and extended family, the bulk of which is from Stout to his wife Margaret and his son Thomas. Correspondents in the Monuments Men correspondence include Thomas Carr Howe, Ardelia Hall, Lamont Moore, Theodore Sizer, Langdon Warner, and many others. There is also substantial correspondence with friends and professional colleagues in the museum and art world, such as Walter Beck, Richard D. Buck, William George Constable, Earl of Crawford, George Peabody Gardner, Jr., William Ivins, Jr., Henri Marceau, and Paul Sachs, among many others.
Writings by Stout consist of typescript drafts and published articles, speeches, and miscellaneous notes. Most of the writings concern art conservation and the speeches are memorials for two of Stout's colleagues. Notes consists of drafts for the texts of holiday cards Stout designed, biographical notes, and images and captions for The Care of Pictures. There are also three conference papers on art conservation written by other people.
Subject files document Stout's conservation projects as a consultant for museums, universities, galleries and other organizations. Also found in this series are documents relating to Stout's work after retiring from the Isabella Gardner Museum and his membership or participation in various arts programs and organizations.
A separate series contains files relating to Stout's World War II service in the Monuments, Fine Arts & Archives (MFAA) Section. Found here are official military records, publications by Monuments Men, and a few scattered photographs. Military records include directives, reports, certificates and a bronze star medal. There are articles and books written by various Monuments Men such as Langdon Warner, Lincoln Kirstein and Theodore Sizer. There are also scattered photographs, only two of which depict tout (including one group photograph with Lamont Moore, Walker Hancock and other Monuments Men.) There are also 12 negatives with 4 prints depicting La Gleize Church and the town of Ambleve, Belgium in 1945. There are also four diaries documenting Stout's experiences in the MFAA Section in Europe and Japan from 1944-1946.
Personal business records include assorted legal and estate papers as well as financial papers such as receipts, travel expenses and donations.
Printed materials consists of news clippings, bulletins, brochures, press releases, conference papers, and magazine and journal articles, most of it related to art conservation.
Artwork includes pencil and ink drawings and sketches, mostly of travel scenes, people, and animals. There is one sketchbook of the human figure. Many sketches were loosely grouped together by Stout with titles such as "Pool Doodles" or "Park and Zoo." The is also one caricature of Eric Brown by Murray Pease.
The papers include photographs and negatives, mostly personal photographs of friends, family, relatives and colleagues. There are also photographs of art conservation conferences and travel photographs. Additional scattered photographs are located in the series containing the Monuments Men files.
Museum directors -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war; Art -- Conservation and restoration; Conservators -- California; Photographs; Arts administrators; Sketches; Sketchbooks; Worcester Art Museum; Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum; Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters. Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section; Fogg Art Museum; Sachs, Paul J. (Paul Joseph), 1878-1965; Gardner, G. Peabody (George Peabody); Ivins, William Mills, 1881-1961; Marceau, Henri, 1896-1969; Hall, Ardelia Ripley; Howe, Thomas Carr, 1904-1994; Sizer, Theodore, 1892-1967; Buck, Richard D.; Warner, Langdon (1881-1955); Constable, W. G. (William George), 1887-1976; Moore, Lamont
- Biographical Materials, circa 1919-1977; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include college and graduate school transcripts, awards and commendations, certificates, passports, and miscellaneous materials such as travel itineraries. There are also four small appointment books dating from 1973 and 1975-1977.
  Arrangement
  The material in this series is arranged in chronological order, except for Margaret Stout's passports which can be found at the end of the series.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Materials which have not been digitized include duplicates and blank pages of appointment books and passports.
  - Sigma Delta Chi Fraternity Certificate, circa 1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University of Iowa Transcript, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - George Leslie Stout Passports, 1924-1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - George Leslie Stout Passports, 1933-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Harvard University Transcript, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clark University Honorary Degree, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Institute for Conservation Honorary Fellowship, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hill-Stead Museum Letter of Appreciation, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poem in Honor of Tavern Club Medal, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Record of Stout Family Reunion, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Appointment Books, 1973; 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Marquis Who's Who Publications Certification, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Appointment Books, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Margaret Hayes Stout Passports, 1930-1938; 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1922-1978; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2.5 Linear feet Box 1-3, OV 8
  Correspondence is with family, friends, colleagues, fellow Monuments Men, and professional organizations such as museums and universities.
  This series is arranged as 5 subseries:
  Missing Title
  2.1: Family, 1925-1978
  2.2: Monuments Men, 1930-1978
  2.3: Friends and Colleagues, 1922-1978
  2.4: Professional, 1925-1978
  2.5: Miscellaneous, 1923-1978
  - Family, 1925-1978; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    Family correspondence is primarily between George Leslie Stout and his immediate and extended family, most of it with his wife Margaret during his World War II service.
    The material in this series is arranged in alphabetical order.
    This subseries has been digitized in its entirety.
    - Hayes, Helen, circa 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Helen Hayes is George Leslie Stout's sister-in-law.
    - Stout, Abe, 1925; 1942; 1972-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Stout, Betty, 1973-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Stout, Carolyn W., 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Stout, Charles H. ("Chick"), 1941; 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Stout, John, 1971-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Stout, LuLu McBride, circa 1926; 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
      LuLu McBride Stout is George Stout's mother.
    - Stout, Margaret, 1943 January-June; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1943 July-October; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1943 November-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1944 January-April; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1944 May-July; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1944 August-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1945 January-March; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1945 April-July; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1945 October-November; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1945 December-1946 February; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Stout, Margaret, 1946 March-1950, 1972-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Stout, Robert, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Stout, Sarah M., 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Stout, Stephen P. ("Tubby"), 1972-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Stout, "Stibbits", 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Stout, Thomas, undated, 1944-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Stout, Thomas, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Stout, Thomas, 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Stout, Thomas, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Stout, Thomas, 1954,1972-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Monuments Men, 1930-1978; bulk 1943-1950; 2.2; Archival Resource Key
    This subseries consists of letters exchanged between Stout and other Monuments Men such as Paul Coremans, Ardelia Hall, Thomas Carr Howe, Lincoln Kirstein, Stephen Kovalyk, Lamont Moore, Theodore Sizer, Craig Hugh Smyth, Langdon Warner, and many others. Several of the Monuments Men went on to prominent careers in the arts and Stout stayed in contact. There is also one letter from Haruki Watsuji, the mayor of Kyoto while Stout was serving as a Monuments Man in Japan after the war. The letter mentions Stout and fellow Monuments Man Langdon Warner visiting Kyoto. There is also a Christmas card signed by members of the U.S. Twelfth Army Group. A few records are in French.
    The material in this subseries is arranged in alphabetical order.
    The bulk of this subseries has been digitized, except for duplicates of letters.
    - Coremans, Paul, 1947-1948; 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - De Vries, A. B., 1975; 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Dixon-Spain, J. E., 1944-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Hall, Ardelia, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Hancock, Walker, 1948; 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Howe, Thomas Carr, 1945-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Includes one color photograph of George Stout seated at a dinner with M.F.K. Fisher and two photocopies of caricatures drawn by the artist Thomas Buechner.
    - Howe, Thomas Carr - Oversized Floor Plans, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 8, Folder 1)
    - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1947; 1961-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Kovalyk, Stephen, 1946-1947; 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Lee, Sherman, 1946-1947; 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Moore, Lamont, 1947; 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Parkhurst, Charles, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Ross, Marvin C., 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Sickman, Laurence, 1946-1947; 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Sizer, Theodore, 1947; 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Smyth, Craig Hugh, 1959-1960; 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Warner, Langdon, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Watsuji, Haruki, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
      There is also a black and white group photograph of Stout with Japanese government officials and two Americans, one is probably Langdon Warner and the other is unidentified.
    - Twelfth Army Group Holiday Menu, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
      This is a Twelfth Army Group Holiday Menu Card for Christmas 1944 signed by several army members of various ranks.
  - Friends and Colleagues, 1922-1978; 2.3; Archival Resource Key
    This subseries contains correspondence with Stout's friends and professional colleagues. Prominent, frequent, or otherwise important correspondents include Walter Beck, Richard D. Buck, William George Constable, Earl of Crawford and Balcarres, George Peabody Gardner, Jr., Rutherford John Gettens, Rollin Hadley, Philip Hendy, William Ivins, Jr., Helmut Ruhemann, and Paul Sachs (Harvard professor and author.)
    The materials in this subseries have been arranged in alphabetical order.
    The bulk of the material in this subseries has been digitized, except for duplicates of letters.
    - Asmus, John F., 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Beck, Walter, 1930-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Brazier, Mollie, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Buck, Robin and Richard, undated, 1971-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Buck, Robin and Richard, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Buck, Robin and Richard, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Carter, Morris, 1938-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cary, Otis, circa 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Colt, Thomas Clyde, Jr., 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Constable, Olivia and W. G., 1933-1946; circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cox, Yvonne, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Crawford and Balcarres, Earl of, 1947-1951; 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Cross, Harold F., 1973; 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - De Wild, A. Martin, 1937-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Ehrlich, William and Evelyn, 1967-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Frederick, John T. and Esther, 1922-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Gardner, George Peabody, Jr. ("Peabo") and Rose, 1954-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Gardner, John Lowell, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Gettens, Rutherford J. and Katherine, 1958; 1970-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Goetz, William, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Gregg, Richard N., circa 1972-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Hadley, Rollin ("Bump"), 1971-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Hayes, Marian, 1947; 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Hendy, Philip, 1947-1948; 1972-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Hodnett, Ted, 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Hunt, Percival, undated, circa 1922-1925; circa 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Ivins, William, circa 1941-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Jacobi, Lotte, 1975; 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)